Karpinski and Sadoski family papers 1901-1981 CPAA 86-31
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University, New Britain
Karpinski and Sadoski Family papers
1900-1981
Sadoski, Aniela Karpinski-
CPAA 86-31
1 box (0.5 linear ft.)
Connecticut Polish American Archives, Elihu Burritt Library, Central Connecticut State University
The Karpinski and Sadoski family collection consists of family photographs taken at the beginning of the century. It illustrates life of Polish immigrants in New Britain and sorrounding towns.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Karpinski family immigrated from Mlawa, Poland to New Britain, CT at the turn of the century. The father, Paul Karpinski was born in Mlawa, Poland, and his wife Fredericka (Karla) Karpinski was Prussian. Both resided in Mlawa, Poland with their seven children before immigrating to America. The children were: Maria (Karpinski) Groblewski, Aniela (Karpinski) Sadoski, Antoni Karpinski, Alexandra (Karpinski) Babinski, Ludwig Karpinski, Boleslaw Karpinski, and Pauline (Karpinski) Nichalowski. Maria married Alexander Groblewski and lived and died in Terryville, CT. Aniela Sadoski settled with her family in New Britain where she was part of the Sacred Heart Church Choir. She worked as a seamstress at the Stipulkowsky Ladies and Gents Tailor Company in New Britain. She later married John Sadoski and moved to Terryville, where she was part of the Terryville Drama Club. Antoni Karpinski lived in New Britain most of his life and later married Johanna Basalaj. Alexandra Karpinski married Wladyslaw Babinski who both lived in Terryville and later in New Britain, CT. Ludwig Karpinski was married but his spouse is unknown. They also lived in New Britain and later moved to New York. Boleslaw Karpinski immigrated to the United States at the age of sixteen and he lived in New Britain, CT. Mr. Karpinski instructed about 4,000 new immigrants about the responsibilities of American citizenship and prepared them to take the U.S. citizenship test. Boleslaw also knew several languages and served as an interpreter in the New Britain police court. He also worked as an insurance salesman for John Hancock Insurance Company. Furthermore Mr. Karpinski also served as a councilman for a short time in New Britain, CT. Pauline Karpinski lived in New Britain, CT. She later married Stanislaw Nichalowski and they moved to Kensington, CT.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The collection consists of photographs of the Sadoski and Karpinski families, who emigrated from Poland to the U.S. and settled in New Britain and surrounded towns in Connecticut. It also includes some genealogical information about both families.
The collection is open for research.
Material in the collection was donated by Mrs. Sadoski-Becker, a daughter of Mrs. Aniela Karpinski-Sadoski in 1986.
Search Terms
Aniela Karpinski; Boleslaw Karpinski; Antoni Karpinski; Polish Americans -- Connecticut.; Immigrants -- Connecticut.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- Societies, etc.; Polish Americans -- Connecticut -- New Britain.; Pamphlets.; Photographs.; Clippings.
Arrangement
Material in the collection is arranged by date.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Wedding photo of Paulina (Karpinski) Nichalowski, 1899-1900 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Early wedding invitation from Boleslaw Karpinski and Stefania Bonkowska, and Aniela Karpinski's choir membership cards for Sacred Heart Church., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Photos of Boleslaw F. Karpinski and article clippings pertaining to his work as a U.S. citizenship instructor., [1959?] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Early photos of unknown family in Ostroleka, and Mlawa, Poland taken at ateliers of Lipszyc, Alpern and Malinowski., undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photo of Choir Group of Sacred Heart church, New Britain, CT., 1906 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Photo of unidentified parish society in front of Sacred Heart church, New Britain, CT., 1903 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Two postcards with image of Boleslaw Karpinski., 1904, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photo of the Stipulkowsky Ladies and Gents Tailor Company, New Britain, CT. Aniela (Karpinski) Sadoski among other employees., [1910?] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Photo of Aniela Karpinski and her brothers Boleslaw and Antoni Karpinski., 1903 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Photo of Walter A. Kozloski, taken in Northampton Mass. The two other men are unknown., 1911 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Photo of Drama Club from Terryville, CT. Contains names of members in photo., 1928 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Photo of the Karpinski family taken in Mlawa, Poland., between 1880-1890 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Photo of a young unknown girl at her first holy communion in New Britain, CT., undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photo of Antoni Karpinski and friends, New Britain, CT., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- "Lubie Czytac" (I Like to Read) exercise booklet for the second grade, printed by the Felician Sisters, (in Polish)., 1946 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Five religious booklets owned by Aniela Sadoski (in Polish)., 1903, 1904, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Z-G Herb Catalog, Chicago, IL, (in Polish)., 1919 (Box 1, Folder 17)